Gebregziabihier Nigusie Birhane

Department of Information Technology, Mizan-Tepi University, Tepi, Ethiopia Phone: +251948725913

Email: gerenigusie138@gmail.com

Personal Statement

Lecturing at one of the Ethiopia University, graduated MSc in 2022 and conducted MSc thesis on Natural Language Processing including three conference papers. In addition to lecturing participated on community service and researches. Have team work experience and interest. Conduct researches on NLP and Computer vision using Machine Learning, Deep learning and Pretrained models is my research interests.

Education

MSc Degree in Information Technology	2020 - 2022
Bahir Dar Institute of Technology, Bahir Dar University, Bahr Dar Ethiopia	
BSc Degree in Information Technology	2015 - 2019
Mizan-Tepi University, Tepi, Ethiopia	
High School	2011 – 2015
Adi-arkay secondary and Preparatory school, Gondar, Ethiopia	
Primary School	2004 - 2011
Bermariam primary school, Gondar, Ethiopia	

Teaching Experience

Lecturer	2022 – present
Assistance Lecture	2020
Graduate Assistance	2019 - 2020

Research Experience

MSc Thesis on Lexical Complexity Detection and Simplification in Amharic Text Using Machine Learning Approach, Bahir Dar University, Bahir Dar, Ethiopia 2022-Presented

Publications

Nigusie, G., Tegegne, T. (2023). Amharic Text Complexity Classification Using Supervised Machine Learning. *Artificial Intelligence and Digitalization for Sustainable Development*

(ICAST 2022). Vol 455, Pages 12-23. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-031-28725-1_1

Nigusie, G., & Tegegne, T.(2022). Lexical Complexity Detection and Simplification in Amharic Text Using Machine Learning Approach. *IEEE 4th Internationa Conference on ICT for Development for Africa*. Pages 1-6. doi: 10.1109/ICT4DA56482.2022.9971306

Conference Presentations

Amharic text complexity classification using complexity annotator tool and supervised machine learning, The 2nd PanAfrican Conference on Artificial Intelligence. Ethiopian Artificial Intelligence Institute, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, October 2023.

Lexical Complexity Detection and Simplification in Amharic Text Using Machine Learning Approach, IEEE 4th Internationa Conference on ICT for Development for Africa. Bahir Dar University, Bahir Dar, Ethiopia, November 2022.

Amharic Text Complexity Classification using Supervised Machine Learning, 10th EAI International conference on Advancment of Science and Technology. Bahir Dar University, Bahir Dar, Ethiopia, November 2022.

Honors and Awards

Best MSc Thesis, Bahir Dar University, Bahir Dar, Ethiopia

August, 2022

Community Involvement

Community service research on Image -Based Mango leaf Pest Identification

Using Deep CNN, Mizan-Tepi University, Tepi, Ethiopia

2023

Community service Project on Android based Covid-19 information management system, Mizan-

Tepi University, Tepi, Ethiopia

2020

Tutorial for Low Grade Students around Mizan-Tepi University

2019

References

Tesfa Tegegne, Assoc. Professor of Computer science Bahir Dar University, Ethiopia +251918762686, tesfat@gmail.com

Alelign Mekonen, MSc in Information Technology Mizan-Tepi University, Ethiopia +251910166150, alelignmekonen@mtu.edu.et